{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In an effort to encourage dental health, this leader encouraged his population to chew on bones because dogs do so. This leader renamed the month of September after his book Ruhnama, whose study is required to obtain a driver’s license in his country. This leader commissioned the construction of an Arch of Neutrality, which contained a golden statue of himself that rotated to face the sun in the city of Ashgabat. For ten points, name this totalitarian ruler of post-independence Turkmenistan from 1991 to his death in 2006.",
      "answer": "Saparmurat Niyazov or Turkmenbashi"
    },
    {
      "question": "Allison Janney earned an Oscar nomination for playing this woman’s mother, the abusive LaVona Fay Golden. This woman followed Midori Ito to become the second woman to ever land a triple axel, but became infamous when her ex-husband, Jeff Gillooly, conspired to attack her rival before the 1994 Winter Olympics. A 2017 film by Craig Gillespie stars Margot Robbie as, for ten points, what American figure skater and rival of Nancy Kerrigan?",
      "answer": [
        "Tonya Harding",
        "Tonya Maxene Price"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The fourth and final section of a book by this man incorrectly tries to explain the origins of Earth’s tides. This man supported one of his arguments by citing the phases of Venus and apparent motion of sunspots. This man introduced the idea of inertial reference frames with a thought experiment about a man below deck on a ship, and wrote a book consisting of conversations between the laymen Sagredo, Simplicio, and Salviati. For ten points, name this author of a Diologue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems, who was charged with heresy for supporting heliocentrism.",
      "answer": [
        "Galileo Galilei",
        "either underlined name"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1910, this state’s constitution almost incorporated the Digges Amendment to disenfranchise African-Americans. Albert Ritchie governed this state for nearly 15 years in the early 20th century. With John McDuffie, a Senator from this state co-sponsored Filipino independence. This state’s flagship law school was integrated after Murray v. Pearson was argued by Thurgood Marshall, a native of this state. H.L. Mencken worked for a newspaper in this state when he covered the Scopes Trial in Tennessee. For ten points, name this state where Congressmen like Millard Tydings represented the city of Baltimore.",
      "answer": "Maryland"
    },
    {
      "question": "An activist from this country mysteriously died while on a U-Boat heading towards his home country during Operation Dove. During World War II, this country was governed by the Emergency Powers Act while maintaining official neutrality. The SS Libau was intercepted before it could supply arms to supporters of an uprising in this modern-day country. Roger Casement was executed for treason as a revolutionary for, for ten points, what country that was led by Eamon de Valera, who fought during the 1916 Easter Rising?",
      "answer": "Ireland or Eire"
    },
    {
      "question": "In a battle in this province, Zhang Shijie was tricked by music to think that the enemy had a banquet. The Battle of Yamen occurred in this southern province, where the Hong factories operated prior to the Opium Wars. The Pearl River Delta lies in this province, which borders the special administrative regions of Hong Kong and Macau. The most populous province in China is, for ten points, what region that contains a city once known as Canton?",
      "answer": "Guangdong"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group was led by the “Fighting Parson” John Elder, and another member, Lazarus Stewart, was killed in the Wyoming Massacre. John Penn placed a bounty on this group, who attacked victims in protective custody at Lancaster. Benjamin Franklin forced this group to disperse at Germantown. This group committed the Conestoga Massacre against the Susquehannock Indians. For ten points, name this group of Pennsylvanian vigilantes who acted against Native Americans in the wake of Pontiac’s Rebellion.",
      "answer": "Paxton Boys"
    },
    {
      "question": "Marie van Goethem worked in this profession and, at age 14, served as a model for a bronze sculpture with a wax-covered skirt. A bronze statuette of a girl wearing bangles was found in Mohenjo-daro in 1926 and is named for this assumed activity. This action is depicted in statutes of Shiva nataraja, in which the god is encircled by a ring of fire with one leg raised. For ten points, name this activity depicted in Edgar Degas paintings of women practicing at the barre or performing in ballets.",
      "answer": [
        "dancing",
        "anything related to dance, including ballet",
        "Little Dancer of Fourteen Years",
        "Dancing Girl",
        "Cosmic Dancer and similar"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This scientist led a task force that outlined plans for a permanent lunar base and a manned mission to Mars in a strategic initiative regarding “America’s Future in Space.” Donald Kutyna was leaked internal documents by this figure, who sat with him on the Rogers Commission. This astronaut was insultingly asked “Will the flight affect your reproductive organs?” before a mission aboard the Challenger. For ten points, name this astronaut, the first American woman in space.",
      "answer": "Sally Ride"
    },
    {
      "question": "Byzantine Emperor Michael VIII claimed in his autobiography that he was God’s instrument to save the people of this region. Pope Adrian IV agreed to the Treaty of Benevento with a ruler from this region. The Hauteville family established this region’s namesake kingdom under Roger II, whose daughter Constance eventually married Holy Roman Emperor Henry V. This island rebelled against the Angevin rule of Charles I during its namesake “vespers.” For ten points, name this kingdom primarily based on an island south of mainland Italy.",
      "answer": "Kingdom of Sicily"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1969, protesters at this university advocated the creation of a Black Studies program during the Allen Building Takeover. This university’s president, Terry Sanford, tried to place the Richard Nixon Presidential Library at this school, which was initially founded by Quakers and Methodists in the town of Trinity. One namesake of this school fought the Black Patch Wars and bought Lucky Strike as head of the American Tobacco Company. For ten points, name this private university in Durham, North Carolina.",
        "answer": "Duke University"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the assassination of Martin Luther King, students at Duke held a week-long Silent Vigil protesting racial discrimination and the non-recognition of Duke’s local chapter in this union for non-academic employees. This union, part of the AFL-CIO, is the largest union of public workers in the country.",
        "answer": "American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees or AFSCME"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this war, an imprisoned king rode across Europe in fifteen days to rejoin his troops, only to die a few years later at the siege of Frederiksten. In this war’s decisive battle, one side’s attempts to appoint Alexander Menshikov as head of the Cossacks led Ivan Mazepa to defect. The Treaty of Nystad ended this war, shortly after military reforms led to a great Russian victory at Poltava. For ten points, name this war in which Peter the Great prevailed over the Swedish Empire.",
        "answer": "Great Northern War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After the Battle of Poltava, Charles XII of Sweden fled to the Ottoman Empire; the Russians were not happy, and waged this campaign from 1710 to 1711.",
        "answer": "Pruth River campaign"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Thisthinkerarguedthattotemicreligionsplayedalargepartindevelopingthecollectiveconsciousness of a people in his Rules of the Sociological Method. In one study, this man pointed to stronger Catholic social controls as diminishing a phenomenon that he divided into egoistic, altruistic, fatalistic, and anomic types. Auguste Comte inspired, for ten points, what author of Elementary Forms of Religious Life and Suicide, a French pioneer of sociology?",
        "answer": "Emile Durkheim"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In his first published work, Durkheim stated that this phenomenon in Society necessitated the development of “organic solidarity” over “mechanical solidarity.”",
        "answer": "the Division of Labor in Society"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Attack ads aired against this man in South Carolina accused him of fathering an illegitimate child with an African-American woman, though the images used were actually of his adopted Bangladeshi daughter. This man, who was permanently injured during a fire on board the USS Forrestal, sponsored a campaign finance reform act with Russ Feingold and entered the Senate by winning a seat vacated by Barry Goldwater. For ten points, name this Vietnam War veteran and longtime Arizona congressman.",
        "answer": "John McCain"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Russ Feingold, McCain’s co-sponsor on campaign finance reform, was a three-term senator from this Midwestern state, which has also been represented by Isaac Walker and Herb Kohl.",
        "answer": "Wisconsin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This initiative may have led to the murder of exiled president Jango Goulart. As part of this initiative, Celestina Almada was forced to listen to her husband Martin’s torture over telephone, prompting a search for documentation of this initiative in the Archives of Terror. Manuel Contreras was one of the early masterminds of this initiative, which was originally run by the DINA secret police but soon expanded to include Jorge Videla’s Dirty War in Argentina. For ten points, name this 1970s-era operation in which South American governments silently eliminated communist dissidents.",
        "answer": "Operation Condor"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One leader who participated in Operation Condor was this Paraguayan dictator of German heritage. During his 35 year rule, he renamed Ciudad del Este in honor of himself.",
        "answer": "Alfredo Stroessner"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In the Aeneid, a god of this domain was the father of Circe, the mother of Latinus. A Roman emperor who worshiped a god of this domain controversially took the Vestal Virgin Aquilia Severa as his fourth wife; that emperor, who gave his name to a deity of this domain, was Elagabalus. A cult centered around an “unconquered” deity of this domain was popular in the Roman Empire until the 4th century. For ten points, give this domain of the deities Sol Invictus and Helios.",
        "answer": [
          "sun",
          "Sol before read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This 3rd century Roman emperor ended the breakaway Gallic and Palmyrene Empires, built a series of walls in Rome, and established Sol Invictus as one of the chief deities of the Roman pantheon.",
        "answer": "Aurelian or Lucius Domitius Aurelianus Augustus, but do not"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man’s negotiations with George Crook were captured in a series of photographs by C.S. Fly. This man participated in a series of conflicts with Mexican troops after his wife and children were killed in a raid led by Jose Maria Carrasco. This man, a de facto successor of Mangas Coloradas, surrendered to the command of Nelson Miles at Skeleton Canyon in 1886. The operation to kill Osama bin Laden was codenamed for, for ten points, what Apache warchief whose name is sometimes exclaimed by jumping paratroopers?",
        "answer": [
          "Geronimo",
          "Goyahkla"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The tradition of paratroopers shouting “Geronimo” legendarily began at this Army base on the border of Alabama and Georgia. Timothy McVeigh met the other conspirators of the Oklahoma City bombings while training at this fort outside Columbus, Georgia.",
        "answer": "Fort Benning"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man addressed deficiencies in message encrypting by adopting the new “Shark” system of communication. Otto Kranzbuhler successfully defended this man’s refusal to help survivors of the Laconia incident, leading him to only be jailed for ten years. After succeeding Erich Raeder in his highest post, this man launched Operation Drumbeat to begin the “Second Happy Time.” He advocated for wolf-pack tactics to win the battle of the Atlantic against allied shipping. For ten points, name this admiral of the Kriegsmarine for most of World War II.",
        "answer": "Karl Donitz"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In the final days of World War II, Karl Donitz became the leader of this short-lived government. Based in a town in Northern Germany, it capitulated in three weeks to the Allies.",
        "answer": "Flensburg Government"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Calvin Coolidge",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "State Coolidge served as Governor.",
          "answer": "Massachusetts"
        },
        {
          "question": "President he succeeded after a fatal heart attack.",
          "answer": "Warren G. Harding"
        },
        {
          "question": "French term for Coolidge’s “hands-off” economic philosophy.",
          "answer": "laissez-faire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Year in which Coolidge was elected to a full term as President.",
          "answer": "1924"
        },
        {
          "question": "Leading third party candidate in that election, a senator who carried his home state of Wisconsin.",
          "answer": "Robert M. La Follette, Sr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Former UK ambassador who finished second in that election.",
          "answer": "John Davis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wealthy Secretary of the Treasury from Pittsburgh who Coolidge inherited from his predecessor.",
          "answer": "Andrew Mellon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who Coolidge appointed Attorney General and, later, to the Supreme Court.",
          "answer": "Harlan Fiske Stone"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Suffragettes Around the World",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Constitutional amendment that gave American women the right to vote.",
          "answer": "19th Amendment to the US Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "American who was arrested for voting in the 1872 election and was briefly honored on American coinage.",
          "answer": "Susan B. Anthony"
        },
        {
          "question": "Deliverer of the “Ain’t I a Woman” speech, a former slave who was born Isabella Baumfree.",
          "answer": [
            "Sojourner Truth",
            "Isabella Baumfree if given before mentioned"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "1848 meeting in New York at which the Declaration of Sentiments, calling for women’s suffrage, was issued.",
          "answer": "Seneca Falls Convention"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group of Americans organized by Alice Paul who kept vigil outside the White House for 2.5 years.",
          "answer": "Silent Sentinels"
        },
        {
          "question": "British family of suffragettes that included Sylvia and Emmeline.",
          "answer": "Pankhurst family"
        },
        {
          "question": "British act that allowed suffragettes on hunger strikes to be released, then recaptured once they’d recovered",
          "answer": [
            "Cat and Mouse Act",
            "Prisoners Act of 1912"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Method by which British suffragette Emily Davison died in 1913, possibly suicidal and possibly in protest, in an accident at the Epsom Derby.",
          "answer": [
            "ran out onto the horse track and/or was hit by a passing racehorse",
            "either",
            "both underlined parts, and descriptions thereof"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Ming Dynasty",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Color of Dehua [day-wha] Ming porcelain, and paired with blue in earlier Chinese pottery.",
          "answer": "white"
        },
        {
          "question": "Eunuch [yoo-nuk] explorer whose massive “treasure fleet” went on 7 voyages.",
          "answer": "Zheng He or Ma He"
        },
        {
          "question": "Complex in Beijing that served as the Ming imperial palace after it was built in 1420.",
          "answer": [
            "Forbidden City or Zijin Cheng",
            "Gugong"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Structure that connected Beijing and Hangzhou, the oldest artificial river in the world.",
          "answer": "Grand Canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Third Ming emperor, who employed that explorer, built that complex, and repaired that structure.",
          "answer": "Yongle Emperor or Zhu Di"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rebel leader who overthrew the Ming in 1644 and ruled the Shun Dynasty for about a year.",
          "answer": "Li Zicheng"
        },
        {
          "question": "1363 battle where Zhu Yuanzhang secured the fall of the Yuan Dynasty by destroying their fleet.",
          "answer": "Battle of Lake Poyang"
        },
        {
          "question": "1449 “Crisis” where over 200,000 Ming soldiers were killed and the Zhengtong Emperor was captured by a small Mongol cavalry force.",
          "answer": [
            "Tumu Crisis or Battle of Tumu",
            "additional information that mentions Tumu"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man’s writings detail Eadburh’s [ed-buh’s] accidental poisoning of her husband Beorhtric [be-oh-trik]. This man, the primary source for the Battle of Ashdown, helped his patron translate Pope Gregory I’s (20 pts)",
        "Pastoral Care, which became the oldest extant book written in English. This man’s most famous work documented the subject’s defeat of Guthrum, creation of the (10 pts)",
        "Danelaw, and rule as King of Wessex. For ten points, name this Welsh bishop who wrote the biography Life of King Alfred."
      ],
      "answer": "Bishop Asser"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This composer called for a piano with lutheal attachment in his violin rhapsody Tzigane. In 1910, this man orchestrated a piece meant to evoke a dancing infanta in Baroque-era Spain. A pair of brothers killed by the same shell in (20 pts)",
        "World War I were eulogized in a “Riguadon” this composer included as part of his Tombeau de Couperin. This composer of Pavane for a Dead Princess also wrote a (10 pts)",
        "repetitive piece for Ida Rubenstein consisting of one long crescendo. For ten points, name this French composer of Bolero."
      ],
      "answer": "Maurice Ravel"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) With the Slavs and the Avars, this empire led a 638 Siege of Constantinople against Heraclius. This empire collapsed to the Islamic Caliphate during Yazdegerd III’s reign. Emperor Valerian I was captured and turned into a human (20 pts)",
        "footstool after the Battle of Edessa by this empire’s King Shapur I. This empire ruled from Ctesiphon signed a Treaty of Eternal Peace with the (10 pts)",
        "Byzantine Emperor Justinian I. Khosrau the Great ruled, for ten points, what Persian empire that succeeded the Parthian Empire and continued to fight Rome?"
      ],
      "answer": "Sassanid Empire"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this state, after the Cockstock Incident, African Americans were banned from residing here and could be punished by Burnett’s Lash law. John McLoughlin was a “father” of this state while working in the Hudson’s Bay Company. Under James (20 pts)",
        "Polk, this region of the United States claimed by Great Britain was annexed in an 1846 Treaty that did not extend the border to (10 pts)",
        "54-40. Lewis and Clark founded Fort Clatsop in this state, the end of their journey to the Pacific Ocean. A namesake trail led to the Willamette Valley in, for ten points, what modern Pacific Northwest state?"
      ],
      "answer": "Oregon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Edward Aethling was brought up in the court of this man’s wife Gisela of Bavaria. This man’s right hand became part of a cult and was stolen by Mercurius. This ruler was either crowned on Christmas or New Year’s Day with a crown from Pope Sylvester II. This Grand Prince succeeded (20 pts)",
        "G´eza and created the Archbishopric of Esztergom. To take power, this man killed the (10 pts)",
        "Magyar prince Kopp´any, who ruled the region near Lake Balaton. Ladislaus I began the canonization campaign for this Arpad ruler and saint. For ten points, name this first Christian king of Hungary."
      ],
      "answer": "Saint Stephen I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This phrase describes the genre of A.E. Housman’s poem “From far, from eve and morning.” One form of this phrase titles a novel in which Dr. Tamkin cons Tommy Wilhelm out of his life savings in the stock market; that novel was written by (20 pts)",
        "Saul Bellow. This phrase, which first appeared in book one of (10 pts)",
        "Ovid’s Odes, describes poems like Robert Herrick’s “To the Virgins, to Make Much of Time” and Andrew Marvell’s “To His Coy Mistress.” For ten points, give this Latin phrase that translates to “seize the day.”"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Carpe Diem",
        "Seize the Day before mentioned"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Joseph Ellicott designed a radial street system in this city, where Joseph Dart Jr. designed the first steam powered grain elevator. From 1882 to 1883, Grover Cleveland served as mayor of this city, which is linked to (20 pts)",
        "Canada by the Peace Bridge. A waiter named James Parker tried to stop an attack in this city, where George B. Cortelyou organized security at the (10 pts)",
        "Temple of Music. The Pan-American exposition was held in, for ten points, what city south of Niagara Falls where Leon Czolgosz [chol-gosh] killed William McKinley?"
      ],
      "answer": "Buffalo, New York"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this war, the USS Baltimore destroyed the city of Iloilo [ee-lo-ee-lo] just hours after soldiers were killed in Santa Mesa. During this war, Jacob Smith wanted to create “a howling wilderness” and ordered his soldiers to kill everyone over the (20 pts)",
        "age of ten. Frederick Funston pretended to be the prisoner of indigenous Macabebe scouts during this war; that trick allowed for the capture of (10 pts)",
        "Emilio Aguinaldo. For ten points, name this war in which American forces put down the Tagalog Republic."
      ],
      "answer": "Philippine-American War"
    }
  ]
}